Hancock, Clarence; Papers apap252
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Clarence E. Hancock Papers
1929-1946
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
apap252
2.0 cubic ft.
The Clarence Eugene Hancock Papers document Hancock's time in the House of Representatives in the United States Congress. He was the representative of the 35th District of New York from 1927 to 1945 but came to represent the 36th district from 1945 to 1947 after New York State was redistricted. The collection includes correspondence, newspaper clippings, Congressional bills, transcripts of Congressional hearings, telegrams, and handwritten notes.
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted.
Acquisition Information
The Clarence Hancock Papers were originally donated to Syracuse University on September 21, 1962 by Hancock's wife and son. The papers were transferred to M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections at the State University of New York, Albany in 2006.
Biographical Sketch
Clarence Eugene Hancock was born in Syracuse, NY on February 13, 1885 to Theodore E. and Martha Hancock. After public school, Hancock attended Wesleyan University in Middletown Connecticut until his graduation in 1906. Hancock graduated from New York Law School in 1908 and was admitted to the bar in the same year. Once he was admitted to the bar, he began to practice law in Syracuse. From 1916-1917, Hancock served as a sergeant with Troop D of the First New York Cavalry, also known as New York National Guard, on the Mexican border. Hancock next served as a lieutenant with the 104th Machine Gun Battalion in the 27th division during World War One. After the armistice in 1918, Hancock was assigned to work as Assistant Division Judge Advocate and promoted to the rank of captain. Hancock continued to serve in the military until 1919.
After finishing his military service, Hancock returned home and became part of the corporation counsel of Syracuse from 1926-1927 and a trustee of Wesleyan University. During this period, Hancock ran in the Republican primary for mayor of Syracuse but lost the nomination. Then, during the 70th Congress, the current representative of the 35th district, Walter W. Magee, died in office leaving his position open. Voters elected Hancock to fill Magee's position in 1927 and he continued to serve as representative of the 35th district until 1945 when there was re-districting. Hancock was then elected as the representative of the 36th district from 1945-1947. While in Congress, Hancock served on the Judicial Committee, Naval Affairs Committee, and Elections No. 1 Committee. Along with this, he was chairman of the speaker's bureau of the Republican Congressional Committee and head of the Eastern Speaker's Bureau in 1936. Hancock was part of the opposition to President Franklin D. Roosevelt's New Deal plan.
Hancock did not seek reelection in 1946 for the next session of Congress because of a long time illness and the recommendation of his doctor that he should rest. After leaving Congress, Hancock returned to Syracuse to practice law but died in a hospital in Washington D.C. a year later on January 3, 1948. He was survived by his wife, Emily W. Shonk of Plymouth, Pennsylvania, whom he married in 1912, and son, John S. Hancock, born in 1914. He is buried in Woodland Cemetery in Syracuse.
The information provided above was gleaned from the following sources
Scope and Contents
Clarence Hancock was a New York State Representative in the United States Congress from 1927-1947. His collection includes correspondence, newspaper clippings, Congressional bills, transcripts of Congressional hearings, telegrams, and handwritten notes. Much of the correspondence is from constituents and fellow Congressmen, and discusses their opinions about a particular bill and the actions they want taken. The collection covers Hancock's official actions as a New York Congressional Representative from 1933-1946 and does not include personal papers or records of his legislative actions from 1934, 1936, 1938 or 1947. Please note that no papers about Hancock's work outside of Congress or the work he conducted as part of the Naval Affairs or Elections Committees are included in this collection. Some areas of interest in the files include the Equal Rights Amendment, Anti-Trust laws, Submerged Oil Lands, War and Emergency Powers, and Bankruptcy hearings.
The majority of the file names are names that Hancock assigned them based on handwritten slips of paper the archivist found within the original folders in the collection. If there was no paper indicating the file's name, the archivist chose a name based on the subject of the records. All the files are arranged alphabetically. Within the files, items are arranged based on the year of their creation.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is arranged alphabetically. There are no series.
Politics and Politicians; Bankruptcy--United States; Insurance--United States.; Court rules--United States.; War and emergency powers--United States--History.; New York (State)--Politics and government; Bills (legislative records); Clippings; Correspondence; Notes; Drafts (documents); Transcripts; Legislative Records; Congressional committee reports; Hancock, Clarence Eugene, 1885-1948; United States. Congress. House.; United States. Congress. House. Committee on the Judiciary.
- Acts, 1941-1946 (Box 1 (Clarence E. Hancock Papers ), Folder 1-2)
- Administrative Law Bill, 1946 (Box 1 (Clarence E. Hancock Papers ), Folder 3)
- Admission of Evidence, 1944 (Box 1 (Clarence E. Hancock Papers ), Folder 4)
- Alien Publication Act, 1940 (Box 1 (Clarence E. Hancock Papers ), Folder 5)
- Anti-Racketeering Act, 1943 (Box 1 (Clarence E. Hancock Papers ), Folder 6)
- Anti-Trust Laws, 1941 (Box 1 (Clarence E. Hancock Papers ), Folder 7)
- Bankruptcy – Misc, 1933; Undated (Box 1 (Clarence E. Hancock Papers ), Folder 8)
- Civil Air Patrol, 1945-1946; Undated (Box 1 (Clarence E. Hancock Papers ), Folder 9)
- Civilian Defense Compensation, 1942 (Box 1 (Clarence E. Hancock Papers ), Folder 10)
- Committee on the Judiciary, 1946 (Box 1 (Clarence E. Hancock Papers ), Folder 11)
- Committee on Juror Selection, 1942 (Box 1 (Clarence E. Hancock Papers ), Folder 12)
- Court Activities Report, 1943 (Box 1 (Clarence E. Hancock Papers ), Folder 13)
- Court Appropriations, 1943 (Box 1 (Clarence E. Hancock Papers ), Folder 14)
- Court Reorganization, 1937 (Box 1 (Clarence E. Hancock Papers ), Folder 15)
- Court Reporters, 1935-1936; 1939; 1941-1945; Undated (Box 1 (Clarence E. Hancock Papers ), Folder 16-18)
- Court Reporters, Undated (Flat-file 1)
- Cox Committee, 1943; 1946 (Box 1 (Clarence E. Hancock Papers ), Folder 19)
- Disqualification of Judges, Undated (Box 1 (Clarence E. Hancock Papers ), Folder 20)
- Equal Rights Amendment, 1937; 1939; 1942-1945; Undated (Box 1 (Clarence E. Hancock Papers ), Folder 21-24)
- Government Employee Loans, 1940 (Box 1 (Clarence E. Hancock Papers ), Folder 25)
- Gwynne Bill-HR 2788, 1945-1946 (Box 1 (Clarence E. Hancock Papers ), Folder 26)
- Harrington Bill, 1939; Undated (Box 1 (Clarence E. Hancock Papers ), Folder 27-28)
- Hatch Bill, 1939-1940; 1942; 1945; Undated (Box 1 (Clarence E. Hancock Papers ), Folder 29)
- Insurance Bill HR3269, 1943-1944; Undated (Box 1 (Clarence E. Hancock Papers ), Folder 30-31)
- Insurance Bill HR3269, 1943 (Flat-file 2)
- Insurance Bill HR3270, 1943-1944; Undated (Box 1 (Clarence E. Hancock Papers ), Folder 32)
- Insurance Bill (1945), 1944-1945; Undated (Box 1 (Clarence E. Hancock Papers ), Folder 33)
- Insurance Bill, 1943-1945; Undated (Box 1 (Clarence E. Hancock Papers ), Folder 34)
- Judicial Salaries, 1945 (Box 1 (Clarence E. Hancock Papers ), Folder 35)
- Kefauver Bill, 1945-1946; Undated (Box 1 (Clarence E. Hancock Papers ), Folder 36)
- Military Order of the Purple Heart, 1946 (Box 1 (Clarence E. Hancock Papers ), Folder 37)
- Miller-Tydings Bill, 1937 (Box 1 (Clarence E. Hancock Papers ), Folder 38)
- Municipal Bankruptcy Bill, 1937; Undated (Box 1 (Clarence E. Hancock Papers ), Folder 39)
- National Stolen Property Act, 1940 (Box 1 (Clarence E. Hancock Papers ), Folder 40)
- Railroad Reorganization (74th Congress), 1935 (Box 1 (Clarence E. Hancock Papers ), Folder 41)
- Railroad Reorganization, 1945 (Flat-file 3)
- Railroad Reorganization, 1945-1946; Undated (Box 2 (Clarence E. Hancock Papers ), Folder 1)
- Receivership and Bankruptcy, Record of Hearing (H. Res 145, Report No.203), Vol 1., Undated (Box 2 (Clarence E. Hancock Papers ), Folder 2-5)
- Receivership and Bankruptcy, Record of Hearing (H. Res 145, Report No.203), Vol 2., Undated (Box 2 (Clarence E. Hancock Papers ), Folder 6-7)
- Receivership and Bankruptcy, Record of Hearing (H. Res 145, Report No.203), Vol 3, Undated (Box 2 (Clarence E. Hancock Papers ), Folder 8-11)
- Receivership and Bankruptcy, 1929-1933 (Box 2 (Clarence E. Hancock Papers ), Folder 12-13)
- Second War Powers Act, 1945-1946 (Box 2 (Clarence E. Hancock Papers ), Folder 14)
- Second War Powers Bill, 1941-1942 (Box 2 (Clarence E. Hancock Papers ), Folder 15)
- Submerged Oil Lands, 1939; 1945; Undated (Box 2 (Clarence E. Hancock Papers ), Folder 16)
- Termination of Temporary Laws, Undated (Box 2 (Clarence E. Hancock Papers ), Folder 17)
- Tort Claims, 1940; 1942 (Box 2 (Clarence E. Hancock Papers ), Folder 18)
- War Contracts Termination, 1944 (Box 2 (Clarence E. Hancock Papers ), Folder 19)
- Wilcox Bill, 1933; Undated (Box 2 (Clarence E. Hancock Papers ), Folder 20)
- Wire Tapping, 1942; Undated (Box 2 (Clarence E. Hancock Papers ), Folder 21)